American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIb. 1807-1825 APS.Archives.IIb APS.Archives.IIb
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - NOT FOUND
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      John Kintzing Kane: Christian Frederick Kaupmann: Sir William Keith: Ed. Klüber: Ludwig Conrad Kuhn: B. Lafon: Bénard de la Harpe: Comte de Langionais: L' Anglois: Lynford Lardner: Lenni Lenape Indians: Lenni Lenape language: Meriwether Lewis: William Lewis: Lewis & Clark Journals: Peter Martensson Lindeström: Robert R. Livingston: Logan (Mingo Chief): Mrs. Deborah Norris Logan:
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      Dr. George Logan: James Logan: London Antiquarian Society: Stephen Harriman Long: Thomas Lowes: Louisiana - Travel and description: David Lloyd: Thomas Lloyd: Joseph McKean: John McKee: David Maclure: James Madison, pres. of U.S.: James Mease: Medicine: Charles Delucena Meigs: Josiah Meigs: Mennonites: William Tuckney Meredith: Mexico: Miami language: Micmac language: Samuel
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      Miller: S. Mills, printer: Mineralogy: Mingo language: Minsey language: David Brydie Mitchell: Samuel Latham Mitchill: Mohawk language: Mohican language: James Monroe, pres. U.S.: Daniel Montgomery: Moravians: Benjamin R. Morgan: Gotthilf Heinrich Ernst Mühlenberg: William Augustus Mühlenberg: Luke Munsell: Nanticoke language: Natick language: Natural history - U.S.: New York literary and
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      philosophical society: John Newnan: Joseph Nicolas Nicollet: Isaac Norris: Joseph Parker Norris: J. P. D. North: North Carolina - Boundaries - Virginia: Onondago language: George Ord: John Ordway: Osage Indians: Panama Canal: William Parsons: Francis Daniel Pastorius: Pastorius family: Robert Paterson: Robert Maskell Patterson: Paxton Boys: John Penn: William Penn:
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      Penn family: Council of Pennsylvania: General Assembly of Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania history: Pennsylvania-Maryland Boundaries: Richard Peters: Thomas R. Peters: John Pickering: George Pollock: James T. Pollock: James Potter: Robert Proud: John Christopher Pyrlaeus: Quadrant: Vicar-General of Quebec: David Ramsay: William Rawle: James Reed: Joseph Reed: Jean Pierre Abel
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      Rémussat: Renoir(?): A. Richard: Mrs. Rivardi: Hugh Roberts: Caesar Augustus Rodney: James Ross: Benjamin Rush: Richard Rush: Jonathan Russel: Joseph Sansom: John Sargent: John B. Sartori: Frederick Christian Schaeffer: Theodore Schulz: Jonas Seely: Thomas Sergeant: Shawnee language: Mrs. Elizabeth Shoemaker: William Short: John Sibley: John Simcock: Abraham
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      Small: Smith: Charles Smith: Daniel Smith: Joseph Smith: Samuel J. Smith: Jacob Snyder, Jr.: Horatio Gates Stafford: William Bacon Stevens: Joseph Story: Thomas Story: John Sullivan: Swedes in the U.S.: Teedyuseung (Delaware chief): Description of Tennessee: Isaiah Thomas: Charles Thomson: William Thornton: James Tilghman: Tench Tilghman: William
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      Tilghman: John Kirk Townsend: John Trumbull: Robert Turner: Elizabeth C. Turnstall: Tuscarora Indians: Job Roberts Tyson: U.S. History - Revolutionary War: Unquachog language: Don Antonio Valdés: Johann Severin Vater: John Vaughan: Roberts Vaux: Hyacinthe Bruscotti de Vestrullo: John(?) Vinall: Birginia - Boundaries - North Carolina: Constantin François Chasseboeuf Volney:
    - Minutes, May 8, Dec. 30, Feb. 13, Aug. 16, July 10, Nov. 3, 1815-1816, 1817-1820, 1840-1843; 13x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      Wallace family: Benjamin Walter: Bushrod Washington: George Washington, pres.U.S.: John Fanning Watson: Isaac Wayne: James Webster: Conrad Weiser: Yates Whely: George Whitehead: Eleazer Williams: Jonathan Williams: Wilson: Caspar Wistar: Thomas Wister: Edward Wright: Vyoming Valley, Penna.: David Zeisberger.
    - Letterbooks, Nov. 4-Oct. 30, 1815-1826; 13x8; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
      D. 3vols. Kept by Peter S. DuPonceau. Presented by P.S.DuPonceau; 27 June 1834. Vol. II, see p. 39 for directions from W. Ward for sending mail to Dr. Wilkins, W.B.Bailey and Lieut A. Lockett; p. 42 for note that Ebeling's successor is E.F.A. Hartmann; p. 47 for address for Pierre Alexandre Vernet; vol. III, see pp. 7, 45, 57, 61, for address for Baron Coquebert de Montbret; p.9 for note of new correspondents, T. Pavenstedt and Gottlieb Ernst Schulze; p. 12 address for Jean Baptiste Say; p. 14 address to send books to LeHavre, France; p. 23 address for Musset Pathay; p. 56 address for Pichon; p. 57 addresses for Mr. Shaler and Mrs. Rivardi; and p. 61 for address for James G. Carter. Tipped in in front of vol. I there are newspaper clippings of professors at Harvard university; vol. II, officers of the Literary and philosophical society of New York; list of Indian agents and superintendents in the U.S.; articles on the growth of of newspapers in the U.S.; advertisement by J. Sonter to sell American publications in Great Britain; and a clipping concerning a French and Indian village in Maine. Miscellaneous notes may be found on page [ii] of vol. II, concerning people who possess knowledge of Indian tongues, expecially John Gambold. Volumes 1 and 2 are indexed. See p. [65] of vol. 1, and p. 61 of vol. 2 for indices.
    - Letter to [John G.E.] Heckewelder, Bethlehem, Jan. 9, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 12.) Printed: APS. Historical and Literary Committee. Transactions, vol. I, [357]-358.
    - Letter to John Sargent, Washington, Jan. 18, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 13.) Sends documents which will entitle the committee to government publications.
    - Concerning the causes of animal heat, Jan. 19, 1816; 10x8; Currie, William, 1754-1828
      Philadelphia, D.S.with initials. 4p.,end. ( see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 46. ) Cf. Minutes, p.460,462.
    - Letter to H[oratio] G[ates] Spafford, Albany, Feb. 19, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 19.) Concerning material for the society. Friendly letter.
    - Letter to W[illiam] Rawle, Feb. 27, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 22.) Concerning a William Penn letter and its prior publication.
    - Letter to Redmond Conyngham, Harrisburg, Feb. 27, 1816; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks. vol. 1, no. 21.) Desires a letter of William Penn and others if possible. Asks state financial aid to publish historical documents.
    - Letter to Joseph McKean, Boston, March 1, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 23.) States purpose of the committee and asks aid. Praises Massachusetts historical society and offers cooperation with it.
    - Letter to David Hosack, New York, March 1, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 25.) States purpose of the committee and offers to cooperate with the New York historical society.
    - Letter to Isaiah Thomas, Worcester, March 1, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 24.) States purpose of the committee and offers cooperation with the American antiquarian society.
    - Letter to Alexander Graydon, Harrisburg, March 4, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks,vol.1,no.27.) Asks for literary aid for the committee.
    - Letter to George Logan, Stenton, March 27, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 31.) States purpose of the committee and asks his aid.
    - Letter to Charles Smith, Harrisburg, March 4, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks,vol.1,no.26.) Desires aid to complete set of volumes dealing with the provincial assembly for the committee.
    - Letter to Charles Thomson, March 28, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol.1, no. 35.) States purpose of the committee and asks his aid.
    - Letter to Isaac Darlington, West Chester, March 28, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 33.) States purpose of the committee and asks his aid.
    - Letter to Miers Fisher, March 9, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p.,end.concerning Fisher's verbal reply. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 28.) Asks aid concerning the calendar of the Quakers.
    - Letter to William Graham, Chester, March 28, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 34.) States purpose of the committee and aks his aid. See letters from Graham to DuPonceau; April 2, 1816;and April 6, 1816, for answers to this.
    - Letter to Caesar A. Rodney, March 27, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 30.) States purpose of the committee and asks his aid.
    - Letter to William Graham, Chester, April 4, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 37.) Thanks for his donations to the committee.
    - Letter to Alex[and[er Graydon, March 27, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 32.) Thanks for gifts to the committee and they would like to have his memoirs.
    - Letter to W[illia]m Graham, April 10, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 38.) Thanks for donation to the committee.
    - Letter to Samuel Coates, Philadelphia, March 12, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 29.) States purpose of the committee and asks his aid. Concerning William Penn.
    - Letter to the President of the A.P.S., May 9, 1816; 10x7-1/2; Austin, James
      A.L.S. 6p.and add.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 89.) Concerning improvements in calculating surveys. Cf. Minutes, p.465, Printed:Trans n.s., vol. I, 181 ff.
    - Letter to W[illiam] Graham, Washington, April 19, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 40.) Asks copy be made of part of a journal for the committee.
    - Letter to John Heckewelder, Aug. 20, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 47.) Concerning Indian linguistics.
    - Letter to J[ohn G.E.] Heckewelder, Bethlehem, Oct. 16, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 50.) Concerning Indian linguistics. Returns the thanks of the committee to him.
    - Letter to J[ohn G.E.] Heckewelder, Bethlehem, Oct. 20, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 52.) Concerning Indian linguistics.
    - Letter to Samuel M. Burnside, Oct. 28, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks,vol.1,no.53.) Presents APS Transactions from the society to the American antiquarian society.
    - Letter to Isaiah Thomas, Oct. 28, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks,vol.1,no.53.) Concerning members for the American antiquarian society.
    - Letter to Abiel Holmes, Oct. 28, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 53.) Answered his last three letters.
    - Letter to George Logan, April 22, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 41.) Thanks of the committee for his aid.
    - Letter to [Jared Mansfield], Sept., 1816; 3x6; American Philosophical Society
      ca. L. 1p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 90a.) Will publish his communication and asks for supplement to it.
    - Letter to Redmond Conyngham, Oct. 18, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of L. 1p. (see APS Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol.1,no.51.) Thanks for aid and asks further favors for the committee.
    - Letter to the President of the A.P.S., Philadelphia, Oct. 6, 1816; 9-1/2x8; L., A. F.
      A.L.S.with initials. 2p.and add.,end. In German. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 39.)
    - Report of committee on the paper concerning the calculation of surd decimalfractions, Nov. 15, 1816; 8x6; American Philosophical Society
      D.S.: R.M.Patterson. 1p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 91.) On same sheet as: Concerning the calculation of...fractions; [read] Oct.18, 1816.
    - Memoranda, March 19-25, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      A.D.S.with initials. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, page 26.) Has spoken with Hopkins, Miers Fisher, Dr. Rose, John James, Beringer, and Mr. Cist for papers for the committee's collection.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Sept. 2, 1816; 9-1/2x8; Mansfield, Jared, 1759-1830
      West Point, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 90.) Concerning his communication to the society on mathematics.
    - Letter to J[ohn G.E.] Heckewelder, Bethlehem, Aug. 27, 1816; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 48.) Concerning Indian linguistics.
    - Concerning the Biblical verse:, 1816; 10x8; L., A. F.
      [ca.]. D. 17p. In German. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 37.)
    - Letter to Abiel Holmes, Feb. 4, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 55.) Concerning Indian languages.
    - Letter to the American philosophical society, March 7, 1817; 10x8; Long, Stephen Harriman, 1784-1864
      [read] A.L.S. 3p.,end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 56.) Concerning the Mississippi, the Illinois and their tributaries. Cf. Minutes,p.470.
    - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, Feb. 17, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 56.) Concerning the manuscript of the North Carolina-Virginia boundary. Concerning Indian languages. Film 199 Frame 129
    - Letter to Francis Lightfoot Lee, May 17, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 57.) States purpose of the committee and asks for his aid.
    - Concerning the climate of New Orleans, May 22, 1817; 10-1/2x8; Barnwell, William, 1758-1827
      [read] D. 22p. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no 47.) Cf. Minutes, p.471.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Sept. 25, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 57.) Concerning Governor Reed's letters.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, June 12, 1817; 9x7; Hassler, F. R. (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843
      New Ark, N.J., A.L.S. 1p. Enc. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 63.) Forwards paper on pyrometer to Patterson.
    - APS. Report..., Oct. 15, 1817; American Philosophical Society
    - Letter to Thomas C. James, Nov. 10, 1817; 10x8; Gråberg, Jacob, 1776-1847
      Tangier, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 59.) Concerning sorghum grown in North Africa.
    - Letter to Jason Chamberlain, Mississippi Territory, Dec. 5, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 58.) Thanks for his aid to the committee. For answer to this letter, see letter from Chamberlain to P.S.DuPonceau; Jan. 27, 1818.
    - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, Montecello, Dec. 5, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 59.) Thanks for documents. Refers to the Lewis and Clark journals. Concerning Indian linguistics. Film 199 Frame 130
    - Letter to Tho[ma]s Jefferson, Dec. 11, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 1, no. 60) Concerning Indian linguistics. Film 199 Frame 131
    - Letter to F[riedrich] von Adelung, St. Petersburg, Dec. 16, 1817; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L. 2p. (see APS Historical...committee Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 61.) Comparative philology.
    - Letter to John Q. Adams, Feb. 16, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 67.) States purpose of the committee and asks aid, especially in Indian languages.
    - Thermometrical observations made during a voyage from Philadelphia to Liverpool and back to Philadelphia, April 3, 1818; 10x8; Hamilton, John
      [read] D. 21p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 68.) Cf. Minutes, p.481.
    - Memorandum concerning Zeisberger's Indian vocabulary, April 29, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, p. 12.)
    - Memorandum, May 5, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, p.12.) Concerning an item of Indian grammar according to Heckewelder.
    - Letter to Professor [Johann S.] Vater, May 4, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks. vol. 2, no. 71.) Neither copy nor resumé made, merely this note that such a letter was written.
    - Letter to John Gambold, May 30, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S.with initials. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 72.) Asks aid concerning the American Indian, especially on the languages.
    - Letter to Joseph P. Norris, June 11, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 74.) Asks for records pertaining to the Indians. For reply to this, see: Norris to DuPonceau; June 19, 1818.
    - Letter to Robert Patterson, Philadelphia, July 8, 1818; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Lambert, William
      Washington, A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 94.) Concerning the finding of longitude. Cf. Minutes, p.482.
    - Letter to James Madison, June 10, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. Enc.wanting. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 73.) Forwards prospectus of volume by the historical and literary committee and asks his aid.
    - Memorandum, July 27, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, p. 15.) Concerning Indians of the U.S. and their grammar.
    - Letter to J[ohn] Vaughan, Aug. 4, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...Committee.) Letterbooks,vol. 2, no. 75.) Concerning Quaker work with the Indians. Refers to Roberts Vaux.
    - Concerning looming and atmospheric refraction, Sept. 6, 1818; 12-1/2x8; Flint, James
      Philadelphia, D.S. 15p.and end.,add: "James Mease," and drawing of 1p. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 71.) Cf. Minutes, p.483.
    - Letter to Daniel S. Butrick, Sept. 7, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 3p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 76.) Asks aid in Indian linguistics. For additional information, see: Butrick Vocabularies (in manuscript file).
    - Letter to John Gambold, Sept. 7, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 77.) Concerning Indians and their languages.
    - Letter to Sir Humphry Davy, London, Sept. 9, 1818; 10x8; Cooper, Thomas, 1759-1839
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 67.) Chemical experiments. Yellow fever. Refers to Jefferson, Madison, and the University of Virginia.
    - Concerning tests on arsenic, Sept. 18, 1818; 12x8-1/2; Cooper, Thomas, 1759-1839
      [read,]. D. 4p. (See Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 96.) Cf. Minutes, p.483.
    - Letter to David B. Mitchell, Georgia, Oct. 10, 1818; Bullock, W. B.
      Philadelphia, L. Copy. 1p. (see APS. Historical... committee. Letterbooks, vol.2,no.78.) Recommends the APS historical and literary committee and asks his aid.
    - Letter to [David B.] Mitchell, Oct. 12, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 79.) Asks for aid in obtaining Southern Indian grammars or articles on Indian customs.
    - Letter to Mrs. Eliza C. Tunstall, Greenville, Mississippi, Jan. 11, 1819; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 2p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 81.) Asks help in Indian languages.
    - Letter to John B. Sartori, Trenton, Oct. 12, 1818; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, L.S. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 2, no. 80.) Asks that he acquire certain books on the Indian languages for the APS.